Alexander N. Charters Papers
Alexander N. Charters Papers
- Syracuse University
  - Kellogg Project
    - Visiting Scholar awards (Box 208)
    - Visiting Scholar conferences, 1989; 1993; 2 folders; material from the first and fourth conferences (Box 208)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 208)
  - Kravitz, Sanford, 1965; address given at SU (Box 208)
  - Library
    See also Library of Continuing Education (LCE).
    - Adult education collections, 2 folders; lists (Box 208)
    - Adult education journals, lists (Box 208)
    - Adult education media, lists (Box 208)
    - Adult education monographs, lists (Box 208)
    - Adult education newsletters, lists (Box 208)
    - Adult education organizations, lists (Box 208)
    - Adult education photographs, lists (Box 208)
    - Clippings, 1967; 1980,; 1998-2000,; 2005-2006 (Box 208)
    - Collection development, SU, drafts of policies for adult education collections, etc. (Box 208)
    - Collection development, general, policies from other institutions; papers on library theory; etc. (Box 209)
    - Correspondence, 1964-2013; undated; 7 folders; undated material includes two poems by Jane Frost, library staff member (Box 209)
    - King & King, Architects, sketch of new Bird Library, proposal, signed by King (Box 209)
    - Library access projects, two separate but related projects
      - Development of Terminology - Adult and Continuing Education, 1976; includes RFP; subject heading/descriptor lists (Box 210)
      - Improved access to information in books / Pauline Atherton, 1975; includes paper by Atherton; subject heading/descriptor lists (Box 210)
    - Omnibus films donation, 1961; 1974-1976,; 1984 (Box 210)
    - Receptionist's procedures for researchers (Box 210)
    - Reports
      - Committee on periodicals and serials, 1972 (Box 210)
      - Increasing the Capacity for Ideas: A plan for developing the library system of Syracuse University, [1965?] (Box 210)
      - Self-study in preparation for the Middle States Association of Colleges and Schools / David Stam, 1986 (Box 210)
      - Training and related issues in Syracuse University Library / Terrance Keenan, [1998?] (Box 210)
    - Retention schedules (Box 210)
  - Library Associates, 1961; 1978-1982,; 1991-1997,; 1999-2000,; 2012; constitution and bylaws, correspondence, invitations, announcements, etc. (Box 210)
  - Library of Continuing Education (LCE)
    - About the LCE, 1964-1965; undated; typescript and printed material relating to the LCE's background, origins, purpose and goals (Box 210)
    - Acquisition lists, 1965-1967; 1971-1974; 2 folders (Box 210)
    - Continuing education abstracts no. 1, [1974?] (Box 210)
    - Contract, 1964 (Box 211)
    - Correspondence, 1964-1968; 6 folders (Box 211)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 212)
    - Directory of Adult Education Organizations, 1968-1970 (Box 212)
    - ERIC Clearinghouse RFP, 1966 (Box 212)
    - Initiators of project, names, c.v.'s (Box 212)
    - Job descriptions (Box 212)
    - Periodical and newsletter holdings, 1974 (Box 212)
    - Proposal, 1964 (Box 212)
    - University adult education, a selected bibliography: Review and topical index / Roger and Karen deCrow, 1967 (Box 212)
    - Word list for indexing adult education documents, 1966 (Box 212)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 212)
  - Maxwell School
    - Center for Continuing Education for the Public Services, joint project with University College (Box 212)
    - Global Affairs Institute, 1995; 1997,; undated; includes brochure, copy of "The intelligent cities project report" annotated by Charters (Box 212)
    - Government Performance Project, 1999 (Box 212)
    - Master of International Public Administration, proposal for creating degree (Box 212)
    - Maxwell School: Past, Present and Future / John Palmer (Dean), 1990 (Box 212)
  - Memo From Syracuse, 1972; notes, mailing list, correspondence (Box 212)
  - Multidisciplinary Institute for Educators of Adults (MIEA), See Academic Institute for Educators of Adults (AIEA).
  - Peace Corps Training, See Professional: Peace Corps.
  - Pi Lambda Theta, 1975 (Box 212)
  - Plumer, Stephen, 1964; two papers on "the benevolent society" (Box 212)
  - Poughkeepsie-Kingston Graduate Center, 1974; report (Box 212)
  - Professional Development Program in Adult Education Syracuse University, by Alexander Charters, 1972; notes, drafts (Box 212)
  - Professional Development Program in Adult Education Syracuse University, by Alexander Charters, 1972; 2 folders; notes, drafts, copies of final report (Box 213)
  - Promotions Manual, undated; final draft (Box 213)
  - Proposals, includes both internal proposals and proposals to various external funding agencies, for projects relating to education, literacy, community development, sensory communication, etc.
    See also Sponsored Programs office, below.
    - Adult Education and Lifelong Learning (ADELL) Clearinghouse, 1977; See Professional: Clearinghouse ADELL.
    - African seminar for University faculty, Nairobi, 1966 (Box 213)
    - Bachelor of Liberal Studies (liberal education for adults), 1965 (Box 213)
      See also University College: Bachelor of Liberal Studies.
    - Center for Instructional Communication upgrades, 1966 (Box 213)
    - Children and families institute, 2002 (Box 213)
    - College credit by examination, circa 1963 (Box 213)
    - Combat writers/directors, US Air Force, 1967 (Box 213)
    - Community antenna television, 1970; See Professional: Community Antenna Television (CATV).
    - Community development, demonstration, training, and research projects, 1964 (Box 213)
    - Continuing education in the Canadian university, 1973 (Box 213)
    - Critical events, adaptation, and adult development, 1964 (Box 213)
    - Equipping a self-instructional laboratory for home economics, 1962 (Box 213)
    - Establishment of a classification system for a national adult education library compatible with machine retrieval and mechanized dissemination, 1964 (Box 213)
    - Evaluation study of programs of liberal education for adults, in the areas of moral and ethical problems, political and social issues, community affairs, aesthetics, and science, 1962 (Box 213)
    - Field school in linguistics, Durango, Colorado, 1966-1967 (Box 213)
    - Foundations of access to knowledge, 1964; summer symposium (Box 213)
    - Graduate fellowship for preparation of college teachers, 1961 (Box 213)
    - Graduate program for preparation of educational planners, 1964 (Box 213)
    - Graduate program in sensory education, 1964 (Box 213)
    - Institute for community college adult educators, 1973 (Box 213)
    - International network in adult education information, 1985 (Box 213)
    - Linguistics, composition, and children's literature for teachers and supervisors, 1965-1966 (Box 213)
    - Longitudinal and comparative study of educational, training, and work experiences of Negro and white high school graduates, 1968 (Box 214)
    - Manpower research and continuing education, 1968 (Box 214)
    - Methods for improving the academic performance of students in engineering, circa 1956 (Box 214)
    - National Library of Science, 1964 (Box 214)
    - National seminar on university urban programs, 1963 (Box 214)
    - NDEA Institute for Advanced Study: Change and continuity in Communist concepts and practices, 1965 (Box 214)
    - NDEA Institute for Advanced Study: Educational media specialists, 1964; six related proposals for training librarians, school media specialists, teachers, etc (Box 214)
    - NDEA Institute for Advanced Study: Remedial reading grades 4-9, 1965 (Box 214)
    - NDEA Institute for Advanced Study: Use of television, K-6, 1966 (Box 214)
    - Nondegree program for Griffiss Air Force Base, 1965 (Box 214)
    - Nurses' training, 1966 (Box 214)
    - Public understanding of social science research in the social problem area, 1968 (Box 214)
    - Regional geography of contemporary problem areas: The Soviet Union and east, south, and southeast Asia, 1966 (Box 214)
    - Romance languages inservice programs, 1968 (Box 214)
    - Study of the finance of evening colleges in the U.S., 1961 (Box 214)
    - Summer institute in mathematics for senior high school teachers, 1965 (Box 214)
    - Summer seminar in African area studies and Swahili, 1965 (Box 214)
    - Syracuse University Youth Development Center, 1963 (Box 214)
    - Training program in developmental psychology, circa 1965 (Box 214)
    - Use of videotape recorder for performance analysis in undergraduate instruction, 1966 (Box 214)
    - Vocational Rehabilitational Administration grant, 1965; with School of Social Work (Box 214)
    - Miscellaneous and/or unidentified (Box 214)
  - Regent Theater, See University Regent Theater.
  - Research patent agreement (blank) (Box 214)
  - School of Education
    - Adult Education Annual Report, 1980 (Box 214)
    - Adult Education Area Report, 1954 (Box 214)
    - Adult Education Area Statement, 1974-1975; several copies, some with annotations (Box 215)
    - Adult education courses, general, 1974-1975; 1977,; 1986,; undated; lists, descriptions, general information; for specific courses, (Box 215)
      See also folders starting with "ATE" below.
    - Adult education program closure, 1991 (Box 215)
    - Adult Education Program Statement (Box 215)
    - ATE 600, 1973; 1978,; 1982-1983,; undated; this course had a number of different titles (Box 215)
    - ATE 611, Survey of adult education, 1974-1979; 1982 (Box 215)
    - ATE 613, Curriculum and instruction at the adult level (Box 215)
    - ATE 614, Problems in adult education, 1964-1965 (Box 215)
    - ATE 621, Futures-Invention: Laboratory in adult teaching (Box 215)
      See also Writings by others: [unknown] / Futures-invention.
    - ATE 680, Curriculum development, 1972 (Box 215)
    - ATE 895 (Box 215)
    - ATE 899, Internship (Box 215)
    - Center for Organizational Research in Education: A Statement of Intentions / Greenfield, Carroll, Blasé, 1977 (Box 215)
    - Committee to Revise Educational Colloquium (Box 215)
    - Communications 1 through 72, 1972-1979; 2 folders; memos and other communications from Charters to faculty, students, staff (Box 215)
    - Core curriculum, 1978 (Box 215)
    - Curriculum review, 1963; undated; includes "Curriculum, curricula: The trail of life in a megaversity" (Box 215)
    - Doctoral dissertations and oral examinations, procedures, memos, guidelines, lists of, etc. (Box 216)
    - Doctoral Review Report; Adult Education, 1979; 3 folders (Box 216)
    - Faculty bios (Box 216)
    - Faculty retreat, 1994-1996 (Box 216)
    - Five Year Plan: Area of Educational Administration and Supervision, 1974 (Box 216)
    - Graduate admissions (Box 216)
    - Ideas for adult education projects at SU (Box 216)
    - Information Resources for Educators of Adults, 1974; seminar; participant list only (Box 216)
    - Information resources for educators of adults / Charters, 1979 (Box 216)
      See also Syracuse University Resources for Educators of Adults (SUREA)/Syracuse University Publications in Continuing Education (SUPCE), below.
    - Instructional Design, Development and Evaluation (IDD&E) program, 1993; 1997,; 2001-2002,; 2005,; 2007; correspondence, course listings, Charters' notes, etc. (Box 216)
    - Lists
      - Faculty and staff, 1975-1976; 1979,; 1989,; 1998,; 2000,; undated; including deans and directors (Box 216)
      - Mailing, various groups (Box 216)
      - Students, 1954; 1974-1983,; 1991,; 1996,; undated; active, dropped, degree recipients, dissertation proposals, etc. (Box 217)
      - Combined, 1979; 1982-1983; students, faculty and staff (Box 217)
      - Miscellaneous, chancellors, committees, deans, trustees, agencies, seminar attendees, etc. (Box 217)
    - Minutes, 1965; 1968,; 1970,; 1972,; 1974,; 1982; various groups (Box 217)
    - Notes, ANC, handwritten notes pertaining to adult education and the school of education (Box 217)
    - Organizational chart, 1992-1993 (Box 217)
    - Overview of the School of Education and an Introduction to Reviews of Doctoral Programs in Education / Burton Blatt and Margaret Early, 1979; prepared for Office of Doctoral Projects, State Education Department (Box 217)
    - PhD requirements (Box 217)
    - Positions vacant (non-SU), 1978; soliciting suggestions from ANC regarding candidates (Box 217)
    - Promotion policies and procedures (Box 217)
    - Publications
      - Adult Educator, 1991-1992 (Box 217)
      - Educator, 1981-1992 (Box 217)
      - Education Exchange, 1988; 1992,; 2000,; 2002 (Box 217)
      - New Horizons in Adult Education, 1991; adult education journal published by the Adult Ed Dept (Box 217)
      - Pedagogy, 1977-1981 (Box 217)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 217)
    - Resumes and c.v's, applicants for various positions in the School of Education (Box 217)
    - Site visit correspondence and schedule, regarding site visit from New York State Department of Education (Box 218)
    - Site visit reports, 1980; regarding site visit from New York State Department of Education (Box 218)
    - Spring conference, 1954 (Box 218)
    - Student body profile, handwritten notes with statistics, summaries, etc. (Box 218)
    - Student files, notes, exam dates, correspondence, etc.
      - Al-Badri, Kais A.H., 1962 (Box 218)
      - Basnyat, Nir Mardan, 1961 (Box 218)
      - Bergeron, Robert, 1963-1964 (Box 218)
      - Breitenfeld, Frederick Jr., 1960 (Box 218)
      - Burt, Marlow, 1962-1963 (Box 218)
      - Flansburg, Edwin W., 1961 (Box 218)
      - Greene, Judith, 1961 (Box 218)
      - Hunyadi, Olive M., 1963 (Box 218)
      - Lepine, Andre, 1962-1963 (Box 218)
      - Malecki, Paul M., 1963 (Box 218)
      - Ouderkirk, Mabel M., 1958-1959 (Box 218)
      - Reiser, Eugene, 1961 (Box 218)
      - Root, Augustin A., 1964 (Box 218)
      - Sayer, Aysel, 1964 (Box 218)
      - Sianipar, G., 1960 (Box 218)
      - Snow, Robert (Box 218)
      - Solt, David O. (Box 218)
      - Warner, Edwin, 1961 (Box 218)
      - Watson, Robert C., 1964 (Box 218)
      - Wolderufael, Abeba, 1960 (Box 218)
      - Miscellaneous, A-Z (Box 218)
    - A Study of Values, 1964; done as part of Education 101 (Box 218)
    - Summer session, 1966-1968 (Box 218)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 219)
  - Shablak, Scott (Box 219)
    See also Academic Institute for Educators of Adults (AIEA).
  - Society of Fellows, 1991 (Box 219)
  - Spitz Advertising Agency, 1966-1967 (Box 219)
  - Sponsored Programs office (Box 219)
    See also Proposals, above.
    - Activity reports, 1964-1966; 1972; 4 folders (Box 219)
    - General correspondence, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 219)
    - General correspondence, 1966-1968; 1973-1974; 3 folders (Box 220)
    - Policies and procedures, 1965 (Box 220)
    - Printed material (Box 220)
    - Teaching/training program briefs, 1964-1967 (Box 220)
    - Teaching/training program summary (Box 220)
  - Student Health Services (Box 220)
  - Study Abroad (DIPA), See Foreign Study Programs.
  - Syracuse Stage, See University Regent Theater.
  - Syracuse University Research Corporation, 1964; printed brochure (Box 220)
  - Syracuse University Research Institute, See Sponsored Programs office.
  - Syracuse University Resources for Educators of Adults (SUREA)/Syracuse University Publications in Continuing Education (SUPCE)
    See also separate collection,
    Syracuse University Publications in Continuing Education (SUPCE)
    - About, papers by Stubblefield and Charters, introductory material, etc. (Box 220)
    - Clippings and printed material (Box 220)
    - Correspondence and memos, 1975-1980 (Box 220)
    - Correspondence and memos, 1981-1988; 1991-1992,; 1996,; 2008,; undated (Box 221)
    - Working notes, 2 folders; drafts, notes, lists, etc, mostly by Charters (Box 221)
    - Miscellaneous, author agreements, lists of acquisitions, order form, etc. (Box 221)
  - 309 Projects, 1972; See Professional: 309 projects.
  - Thursday Morning Roundtable (TMR), See Professional: Thursday Morning Round Table.
  - Tieline Magazine, 1963-1964; correspondence, special issue "Honor Roll Syracuse University Faculty" (Box 221)
  - Tolley Medal
    - Awards dinners, 1966; 1969-1971,; 1973,; 1975,; 1983,; 1986,; 1994; 2 folders (Box 221)
      Folders include invitations, programs, and in most cases a printed copies of the address given by the recipient (sometimes referred to as the "Tolley Series"), as follows:
      TOL 1 Houle, Cyril O. "The Uncommon School" (1966)
      TOL 2 Mehta, Mohan S. "The University and the Community Man" (1969)
      TOL 3 Raybould, Sidney Griffith "Universities, Adult Education, and Social Concerns" (1970)
      TOL 4 Bartlett, Kenneth Gill "Toward Still Greater Professionalism" (1971)
      TOL 5 Kidd, James Robbins "Relentless Verity: Education for Being - Becoming - Belonging" (1973)
      TOL 6 Bown, Lalage "A Rusty Person is Worse Than a Rusty Nail: Adult Education and the Development of Africa" (1975)
      TOL 7 White, Thurman James "The Promise and Pragmatism of Adult Education" (1979)
      TOL 8 Bertelsen, Paul Henry "United Nations Education, Scientific and Cultural Organization" (no copy of address in the collection) (1983)
      TOL 9 Charters, Alexander N. "Some Perspectives on Lifelong Learning"( 1986)
      TOL 10 Stern, Milton Reid "K Through 60 and the University's Role Therein" (no copy of address) (1994)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1987; 1994,; undated; bulk is from 1986, the year that Dr Charters received the award (Box 222)
    - History and procedures (Box 222)
  - Tolley, William Pearson
    - Correspondence, 1963; 1966-1967,; 1980,; 1987,; 1996; includes letter to Carnegie Corporation, programs from 80th birthday celebration and memorial service (Box 222)
    - Adult education at Syracuse University - Past and future, 1958; address given at Minnowbrook (Box 222)
    - American universities in transition and the new role of adult education, 1967; 4th Mansbridge Memorial Lecture, Leeds University (Box 222)
    - Continuing education and public responsibility, 1960; SUNY publication; contains "Adult education: A new mission for a new day" by Tolley (Box 222)
    - Design for adult learning, 12 Oct 1959; 17th Annual Southwest Conference on Adult Education, University of Texas (Box 222)
  - The Tolley Years interview transcript, 1982; 2 folders; Mike Sawyer and Bruce Thompson interview Alex Charters for their book "The Tolley Years"; 2 copies, one appears to be incomplete (Box 222)
  - United States Air Force foreign language training, 1967 (Box 222)
  - United States Army, 1988; appraisal of curriculum of Army Comptrollership School at SU (Box 222)
  - University College
    - 75th Anniversary celebration, 1993; correspondence, printed material, photographs (Box 222)
    - Academic Planning Study, 1967 (Box 222)
    - Annual reports, 1954-1966; 1969-1977,; 1980; 2 folders (Box 223)
    - Bachelor of Liberal Studies (BLS) program, 1965 (Box 223)
      See also Proposals: Bachelor of Liberal Studies.
    - Bachelor of Professional Studies, 2001 (Box 223)
    - Biographical material on administrative staff, 1963-1964 (Box 223)
    - Clippings, 1959; 1991,; 1994,; 2007 (Box 223)
    - Continuity and change in university adult education / L. L. Smith, circa 1865 (Box 223)
    - Correspondence, general, 1948; 1956-1959,; 1962-1965,; 1969,; 1994,; 2004 (Box 223)
    - Dynamics of change in the modern university: Implications for adult education, 1965; summary of conference sponsored by UC (Box 223)
    - Local community leadership / Linton C. Freeman et al., 1960 (Box 223)
    - A period of transformation, 1958-1965, 2 copies (Box 223)
    - Planning questionnaire, 2 copies (Box 223)
    - Present role of University College, Alexander Charters, 1959; conference address (Box 223)
    - Printed material, 1956-2014; commencement programs, brochures, newsletters, "The story of Pinebrook" by Applegate, etc. (Box 223)
    - Relationship to other campus colleges, 1958; 1989 (Box 223)
    - Reports to Board of Trustees, 1957-1958; 1985 (Box 224)
    - Sponsored programs, 1965-1966 (Box 224)
      See also Sponsored Programs office (above); Proposals.
    - Staff Conference, May 1958 (Box 224)
    - Miscellaneous Charters-related material, lists, summaries, projects, awards, etc. (Box 224)
    - Miscellaneous, organization chart, list of staff, MOU with Syracuse Chorale, ideas for projects/programs, etc. (Box 224)
  - University Regent Theater (Box 224)
    Charters was involved in the formation and establishment of the University Regent Theatre, which later became Syracuse Stage; material here thus includes University Regent Theatre, Syracuse Stage, and SU Theatre Corp.
    - Charter, S.U. Theatre Corporation, 1962 (Box 224)
    - Correspondence, 1958-1968; 1985,; 1997,; 2000-2002,; undated; 6 folders (Box 224)
    - King & King, Architects, 1963-1967 (Box 225)
    - Programs, See Memorabilia: Programs: Syracuse Stage.
    - Reports, annual and otherwise (Box 225)
    - Syracuse Stage 40: Celebrating 40 Seasons, published book; includes mention of Charters (Box 225)
    - Trustees' meetings, 1995-1996; 2001-2002 (Box 225)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 225)
  - US-Brazil Higher Education Consortia Program, 2001 (Box 225)
  - Wilmot, Robert, 1964 (Box 225)
  - Work Programs for Comprehensive Planning, 1965 (Box 225)
  - Miscellaneous, 1941-2014; 2 folders; mostly printed matter, including brochures, newsletters, announcements, booklets, etc.; includes commemorative booklet from Syracuse University Secretaries First Birthday Party (1941) (Box 225)
- Writings
  Writings includes proposals, reports, monographs, books, periodicals, speeches, and memoranda by Dr. Charters, as well as some works by other authors. Writings by Charters are given first, followed by writings by others and finally writings by unknown authors.
  Many of the items in this series are listed in Jane Frost's bibliography, Historical and Research Materials Related to Adult and Continuing Education (1992), a copy of which is in the first box in this series. In generating her bibliography, Ms. Frost assigned each subset of material a three-letter code. In the inventory of writings which follows, documents which appear in Frost's bibliography include this three-letter code in square brackets following the document title -- for example "Accent on Action: A Ten Year Report 1950-1960 [Frost ID: ANC 7]". Occasionally items were re-issued, resulting in more than one Frost ID number.
  For completeness, all items by Dr. Charters which are listed in Frost's bibliography are also included in this inventory, whether or not they are physically present in this collection. Those which are physically part of a different collection are indicated in the inventory below as "See [name of collection]." Those which have been cataloged are indicated in the inventory below as "See ." Those for which no copy presently exists in any collection are noted in the inventory as "Not present in the collection." Per Jane Frost's bibliography, two numbers were not used: ANC 10 and NPU 26.
  In addition, many of these items were published by Syracuse University Publications in Continuing Education (SUPCE), which assigned its own alphanumeric code. That code is also given, where applicable; for example, "eventually published as SUPCE MSS 34".
  - Lists of
    - Historical and Research Materials Related to Adult and Continuing Education / Jane Frost, 1992; Comprehensive bibliography of Charters' writings up to 1992, including documents written by others at his request. Prepared by Jane B. Frost in 1993 and published under the auspices of Syracuse University Publications in Continuing Education (SUPCE), it also appears in that collection as MSS 35. (Box 226)
      For earlier edition, see Frost, Jane B. / Historical and research materials related to adult and continuing education (below), or see